welcome to meditating with john vervicky
this is the last time we will be live
streaming on a weekday
starting next week uh september the 12th
we will be moving to saturdays from 10
a.m
to 11 a.m and every uh one of those days
will be a dharma day
we're going to continue working our way
all the way through
the wisdom of hypatia i'm committed and
my team is committed
to guiding you guys all the way through
that
course that will take us through the
three degrees of the western wisdom
tradition
if you're joining us for the first time
don't be put off by this unusual setup
there are lots of videos available for
you teaching you
basic uh meditation contemplative
practice moving mindfulness practices
uh go to the links in the description do
lesson one and then do
one or two lessons every week and then
what you can do is keep meeting with us
on
saturdays from 10 a.m to 11 a.m eastern
time you
can also join the discord server uh the
links will are in the
in this video description of this video
and there they are doing regular sitting
they're sitting uh twice
a week they are doing uh other related
practices that have been taught in this
course like group lectio divina
uh the movement practices they're going
to be homing a practice i'm going to be
reviewing today
uh which is for philosophical
contemplative companionship which is a
core practice
within the extended epicureanism that
we've been learning together
i would ask you all to help me by liking
this video
and this video and maybe the channel as
a whole
as a way of raising its visibility in
the youtube algorithm
at the end we will have some questions
so here's what's going to happen
we're going to sit first obviously we're
going to do some chanting
and then we will have our silence set i
will get up and move
we're going to cut from one camera to
the other but hopefully the technology
will
uh stay with us
lamar and jason are behind the scenes
really making things work
and i will review uh what we did on
monday about philosophical
contemplative companionships then i'll
return here to sit
and i'll answer some questions you might
have please limit the questions at that
time to anything from the entire ecology
of practices
and i will give priority to questions
concerning this most recent practice
that we're learning
the philosophical contemplative
companionship
which we've drawn from the work of rand
lahav
and so i think without any further ado
we we can get ready to begin so please
get yourself in your basic position
uh we will begin together when i save
again we will start as i said with
chanting
and then we will go into our silence
begin
[Music]
one
home
[Music]
on
one
[Music]
on
one
begin your silent set
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you've
cultivated in your practice with your
everyday consciousness cognition
character and communitas perhaps by
reciting
the five promises
uh
all right so let's review what we've
been talking about
uh with philosophical contemplative
companionships reminder that we're
making use
of the work of lahav
here's one of the books that's the main
one we're using
another one that's relevant
is this one
and then behind it
is this more comprehensive work
i'm not expecting you guys to read this
it's just there's a resource my job is
to help
translate it to you so let's remember
the three things we're trying to do
and we're making sense making sense of
the text
i'm going to use ms for making sense
making sense of ourself and making
sense of others and these
three are mutually inter-penetrating
interdefining
and inter-affording
okay so we talked about making sense
of the text and what were some of the
core principles we've discussed
uh we discussed that we're going into an
adverbial mode
we are trying to if we're reading
a text by plato we're trying to learn to
see the way plato did to see things
platonically
to hear things platonically to speak
and that leads us into that we're trying
to envision
right we're envisioning we're trying to
see right the way
uh plato died or epicurus or marcus
herrellius
and we are trying to invoke
the presence of that person we're trying
to give voice to them
we're trying to feel the presence and
this takes us into a different
orientation with the text we're not
trying to
just gather information from the text
we're trying to presence the person
of the text for transformation
and this is an idea that uh leo ferrara
and i talked about
myself from leo ferraro and uh the
chapter we
published in um
a scientific study of personal wisdom
from contemplative traditions to
neuroscientific investigation or
something like that i think it was 2013.
and we talked about a practice called
internalizing the sage
so we have this term right of a role
model and it comes up in things like
coaching
right what's a role model so i mean one
of the things
you learn as a parent is kids pay way
more attention to what you do
because they're imitating you than what
you say
because they're not largely trying to
store propositions from you
they're trying to transform themselves
into persons
role modeling is about the process of an
imitation
a mimetic activity so that we come to be
like the person
and this goes to uh internalizing the
sage
this notion of internalization comes
from
the developmental psychologist vygotsky
one of the greats
uh second only to piaget and vygotsky
talks about a process
so let's remember the the metaphor that
we're using here
as the child is to the adult
the adult is to the sage
the text is we're trying to write
personify in a very powerful sense we're
trying to personify the text
we're trying to personify and presence
the sage
so what vidatsky talks about is let's
say here's a here's my
my one of my sons when they're younger
here's me
and here's a problem that right now my
son can't solve that problem at all
he has a particular perspective on it
and that perspective's not quite working
now what i have is i have a perspective
that encompasses both his perspective
and my perspective and what he does
is he tries to imitate me because
he when he when he's within this
perspective he can't see the biases of
this perspective
and he can't see goals and values that
lie
outside the perspective i can see those
goals and values
and i can also see the biases within his
perspective and by
imitating me right by trying to
presence my perspective and envision it
and invoke it he eventually gets this
ability
to take my perspective on his
perspective
and then he internalizes that ability it
becomes an ability that he has for
himself
he can step back and look at a
perspective he can reflect upon it this
is how we get what's called
metacognition this is our our awareness
of our own
foot thinking and reasoning meta
above and beyond like metaphysics
metacognition
but as the child is to the adult the
adult is to the sage we want to presence
the perspective of the sage so that we
can
self-transcend transform we can
self-transcend
by internalizing the perspective of the
sage
that will help us to see the biases of
our everyday perspective
and it will help us to envision and
taste
values and goals that are not available
to us
from within our perspective this is
primarily how we aspire
so what we're doing is we're in we're
trying to envision
the text we're trying to invoke for
internalization
the presence of this age so that we can
role model
it to each role model that person that
personification to each other
okay making sense of others
so we talked about creating a space
within ourselves a silent sensitive
space and we're letting what other
people say
reverberate in us very much like what we
do with lectio divina and the text
and we are also trying to internalize
the perspective of others
so the sage is an important voice
maybe right the central voice but all
the other voices are important too we
are forming a chorus of voices
and each person is like a mirror of all
the other voices we're internalizing
them
and trying to self-transform
in that fashion okay making sense of
others
sorry making sense of self
sorry i already did this making sense of
the text
making sense um of others making sense
with others so
okay so what we're doing here um
sorry i think i did the wrong thing at
the beginning i i put up three things i
meant making sense of the text making
sense of others and making sense with
others i apologize for that mistake
i put making sense of self here uh
that's it that's a mesh in all
of all three of these so please note
that that's a mistake
i apologize the triad should have been
making sense of text
right making sense of others
and then making sense with others i
apologize for that mistake
okay making because i was what was in my
mind was i wanted to convey
the the self transformation the self
transcendence
so that was uppermost in my mind that's
why i made that mistake
okay making sense with others what we're
trying to hear
do here is we're trying to resonate
right
so when we're speaking we're trying to
resonate and when we're listening we're
trying to resonate with others
and we're trying to incorporate what
others say whenever we speak
we don't speak as if we're a monolithic
isolated voice
i pick up on what other people have said
and what the text has said
and i incorporate it in like a jazz
musician
and i try to resonate with what other
people
are saying so what does that mean when
we're making
sense with others i'm not going to
engage in agreeing or disagreeing with
the text
i'm not going to evaluate the text i'm
going to avoid speaking automatically
i'm going to avoid speaking from
autobiography and i'm going to avoid
speaking from
authority i'm trying to break monologue
so that i can make real dialogue
possible
not pretended dialogue within the safe
security of my egocentric monologue
but general genuine i mean in general
genuine dialogue which is vulnerable and
open to other people
so i'm i'm not trying to primarily
explain the text i am
trying to exemplify it
that's how i'm going to make sense with
others we're going to give
voice we're going to presence we're
going to resonate we're going to
incorporate
so i talked about 3d
co-emergence
i want to get the depth of the text
i want to get the depth of the self
you can see that's where the confusion
came into my mind and i want to get
the depth of others
okay these are all co-emerging together
3d co-emergence
when when we talk about getting to the
depth of the self
think of that aspirationally it means it
does mean
getting to that silent space and trying
to speak from the depths
but the depths are aspirational right
they're not a secret
secluded self the depths of yourself are
those parts
that are now coming into emergence
all right so we talked about the basic
setup
we talked about a four by four four
people that commit to four meetings
about an hour to an hour and a half long
there's going to be a facilitator
at each meeting one of the four people
and then that's going to rotate with
every meeting
what the facilitator does is it organ
they organize the order
uh of the people there thank you for
doing it online which would probably be
um a good uh idea
is alphabetical order and each person
memorizes who comes before them and who
comes after them take a few moments to
do that
the facilitator is also going to guide
people through the practice
right and the basic sequence is the
facilitator welcomes people
right then we set up the core four
everybody font does you write the
finding their center finding the root
finding their flow finding their focus
right then we do the main exercise
which i call the ritual enactment
and then d we do take away
don't forget the takeaway the takeaway
is very important that's an important
pedagogical principle
okay
what are the procedures we talked about
the various procedures one is slow
reading
some core uh interaction with the text
uh so you're re you're reciting the text
not just reading it
it's like it's like lectio recitation
you're reciting it the way you do
in lectio divina you're pausing so that
people can
uh gather and internalize and what
you're doing
also is right everybody is trying to
internalize the text that is
as it is being written they're trying to
put into practice all those principles
i've been talking about we have
precious speaking
so you're trying to hear you're going to
respond to the text there's going to
like i'll mention this later you have a
question
impression speaking your response you're
trying to say as much as you can
with as few words as possible one or two
sentence
maximum and what you're trying to do is
you're trying to
savor what you're saying you're not
trying to speak about the text
or just respond to the text you're
trying to speak through the text
right you're trying to do all that stuff
i said about you're trying to
internalize
the platonic or the socratic vision
you're trying to presence the sage
you're trying to speak through the text
you're trying to write
see through the text and beyond the text
and by means of the text
the text are your glasses by which you
train yourself to envision the right
adverbial to see as the see
the sage sees okay so that's precious
speaking
we're savoring we're deeply savoring
and you're speaking to resonate with the
people around you
you're trying to set up the concert of
the chorus of voices
you're trying to speak in concert think
about that speak in concert
to create a chorus of voices
finally i'm one more point for precious
speaking
you're always speaking to presents
you're trying to do
the 3d co-emergence so
that's the one the main thing you're
trying to do is to
it's almost like magic you're trying to
speak into existence you're trying to
invoke
forward evoke 3d
co-emergence of depth okay
so now intentional
conversing
so there's of course now it's
between people and what we're doing here
is remember we're listening when other
people are speaking we're listening from
the depth
um we're creating that inner right
that inner silent space of receptivity
so that people can
the people's words can reverberate
within us when and we're savoring what
other people are saying we're
savoring it that's why you're doing all
this savoring practice
we're bearing witness to epiphany to use
rusin's beautiful phrase
we're bearing witness like the
witnessing of a birth of a child
you're trying to bear witness to people
like we're midwifing each other to use
the socratic metaphor
we're trying to bear witness to the
birthing of people
and the birthing of the personification
of the sage
we're bearing witness to conception and
birth in a deep sense of that metaphor
when we speak of course what we're doing
is we're doing extended precious
speaking
now right where we for president
speaking we speak for about one or two
sentences
in intentional conversing we speak for
about one or two minutes
maximum one or two minutes maximum and
what we're doing is as we're speaking
right we're speaking in the way
in the in the manner and the way we do
precious speaking we're just
extending it now it's more responsive
and of course we're always trying to
speak to resonate with others we're
speaking in concert for a quarter of
voices
we're trying to speak right into we're
trying to speak
into existence 3d co-emergence
then the next one right is uh
rheumatadio
philosophical chanting the facilitator
will pick
a sentence from the text make sure that
everybody has a basic understanding
and then in sequence in the in the
proper order
people chant and you have chanting
practice
chant that sentence when you are not
the person actually vocalizing you are
silently reciting
the text with the person who's chanting
at the end of every round
there is a pause so people can gather
right the logos can take shape
uh within them and of course all the way
throughout
we are savoring we are savoring we are
savoring
all right so
what's the main exercise the ritual
enactment
we start with slow reading
then we move into rumutatio
then we do precious speaking
and the precious speaking is in response
to
a question which can be spoken by one of
the group or perhaps
the facilitator what is the text
provoking
or invoking within you and between us
what is the text provoking or evoking
and the precious speaking is a response
to that question and you do that
for as many rounds as you wish to do
and then you move into intentional
conversing
and then the fifth thing is the takeaway
the facilitator announces that the
intentional conversing is over
everybody can step into a more
reflective explanatory
autobiographical mode here's where you
go into explanatory
autobiographical reflective mode and
what are you taking away from this
session
what are you taking away how how is this
touching you personally
how are you going to transfer this into
your life how are you going to integrate
this
into your everyday consciousness
cognition character and communitas
final thing where would this sit within
the overall ecology of practices
that's hard to say because we're still
working through the western tradition
what i would recommend perhaps right now
is that if
uh for example on the discord server you
might want to
alternate uh between lectio divina
and uh philosophical contemplative
companionship because they really do
and this metaphor really sings now they
really do speak to each other
in a powerful way but i don't want to
mandate
i i don't have that authority or the
relevant expertise
i think but you know if you have people
doing lexio
in one and also pcc
separately that's fine but getting it it
would be
optimal to my mind that if people were
practicing both
in some kind of tandem relationship
because they they have they speak to
each other they correct
and afford each other okay
so that's everything again sorry for the
small glitch
um in the presentation i hope that was
clear
and a helpful uh review
i'm going to now move back uh to the
cushion so i can more properly see the
tv
and we'll address any questions
that might be coming up
great and uh grenin
i've just started interacting with the
sang this week and i noticed a lot of
contraction in my body as well as what i
would call selfing
as i interact with the other egos can
you uh
recommend so i don't remember what
lesson it is
in fact i talked about it at various
places you might want to take a look at
michael washburn's book the ego on the
dynamic ground because he talks about
um a phenomena called body armor the way
in which and
this is also coming out now in more
recent work on trauma the way
we store right um
and we i like your verb we self and we
store
um certain patterns of how we frame
and identify things in situations in the
world and i
and assume identities in response all
that selfing is
a deeply embodied and often um armored
way we contract and
we hold um and so one of the things to
do
is to get very deeply into the core four
especially uh finding your flow finding
your center finding your group finding
your flow
these really open up your body make sure
you're finding uh
the focus that's the soft vigilance
because a hard focus kind of
concentration which is not right
concentration
is conducive to that er you know
contracting
and holding you want the soft vigilance
um taking up
practices like lectio divina tend to
open us up
to perspectives other than our our own
in
a way that it is much more nurturing and
inducing it draws us out that's what the
original meaning of education
to a deuce to draw out you want to
hopefully you've perhaps learned where
we've talked about the five factors of
inquiry mindfulness
i believe that's lesson six we talked
about
how to do meta uh which is lesson five
learning how to do meta towards those
areas
applying the five factors of acquiring
mindfulness to those areas of
contraction
that sense of you know like like you
said we're sort of selfing
uh learning to uh come into a proper
relationship
of mindful uh befriending of those air
of that that contracting and selfing um
through these kinds of practices is a
powerful way uh to
build up a
transformation uh the reason i'm
hesitating is
uh the the over your overall attitude
and framing of this has to be one of
befriending
you have to let it you have to be
patient like a friendship you have to
let it unfold at its own pace
so you have to have the diligence right
the commitment
to being present and engaged and
receptive and responsive
but you also have the patience to let it
unfold
as it will so karima
cynthia clayton hey karima it's it's
always wonderful
to get your questions or observations
observation my mind has become clearer
more organized
friendly free more than knowledge every
day you brought hope for the journey of
the awakening heart within
group communion only this evolves us
um thank you karima that's wonderful
to say for you to say that um first of
all it's encouraging to me
um and so i do appreciate that i hope
it's encouraging to everyone else
um these so this is going to be an
ongoing thing remember
do not just share your questions they
are valuable and important
but sharing your observations your
edifications your
mutual encouragement right that's that's
such an
epicurean thing to do mutually
encouraging each other
um this is very valuable this is uh
very important i i released a video
yesterday with
jordan hall and jordan has a wonderful
saying uh which we discussed at length
and
um i i discussed something that had
really touched me i just finished
reading
alberto camus the plague and i was
touched
playing with something that touched me
but what and we put these two into
dialogue but he has this thing he says
he says the next buddha will be the
sangha and that's i think that's just
profoundly right
given what we're facing we're going to
need we're going to need collective
intelligence and more so than that we're
going to need collective wisdom
um for what's coming and that's what we
have been building here the next buddha
is the sangha
so encouraging and edifying each other
with these kinds of observations and
sharing
are just as important as the asking of
questions
pedro acosta can you advise how to
meditate with eyes open
i can't very much because i don't have
much
experience and therefore not much
relevant expertise i can pass on what
i've learned
mostly second hand with a couple of uh
first time
first person try first person
perspective tries actually trying it
firsthand that's what i'm clumsily
trying to say
right um so the idea is to keep your
eyes open
and generally uh semi closed and
looking down onto some place on the
earth that you pick as the spot
as your meditative focus you don't want
to be sort of
up and like this because that really uh
opens you up now
that that sort of stance is is uh
you know appropriate for some of our
moving contemplative practices
but if you're actually trying to engage
in meditation
right you want the so uh
austin the guy who had zen of the brain
and other work he has research showing
that when you look
up like this it takes you into the third
person perspective processing areas of
the brain
and when you look down like this it
shifts you into the first person
processing areas of the brain so it's
important but but
do that without tilting your head right
so you have to pick something sort of
i'm doing it so you can see it in the
camera but that means i'm tilting my
head
but you want to be i semi-closed looking
out
right onto a space on the ground that's
i don't practice that way so i can't
give you much more than that
uh i i understand some of the basic
reasoning
why you would engage your way you do
i've only tried it once or twice
i don't have a lot of confidence in it
and it's especially important
to to make sure that
when you're looking out you're that's
not
excessively triggering mind wandering
i think it's important to do open eyes
practice very much
and that's where all the moving
mindfulness practices work for me the
moving minded
mindfulness practices that i've taught
you and also the tai chi chuan and other
things
that's where i do the open-eyed
mindfulness practices
matthew mccready question i've been
trying to change my attitude towards
those around me who seem to
live an unexamined life i've been
dealing
directing meta towards them to see their
mourners and bring
more compassion towards them but i still
don't have an understanding
of how they can live that way is an
understanding necessary or is compassion
enough
that's a hard question to answer depends
what you
want the understanding for um so
there's an important sense in which
understanding something more deeply
in fact enables our compassion but
i wouldn't want to say that simply
having a a theoretical understanding
is any kind of replacement if you have
to choose or prioritize
the compassion is more important but i
have found
and i try to practice it i was packing
this last night in a conversation
i have found that if i can try and get
compassion and understanding
to well dear logos with each other they
do mutually afford each other
um so trying to remember so every day i
make a commitment to myself
to be to try to be honest because i know
the sting of deception
and to be honorable because i know the
sting of disappointment
and to be humble because i know this
thing of arrogance
and to be helpful because i know the
sting of fate
we have to we have to remember there's a
thing called the fundamental
attribution error the fundamental
attribution error is when we
see other people flaws we tend to
attribute it to their character
and when we see their a success we tend
to attribute to their circumstances
so he just wow that was a bad thing he
must be a horrible person
oh that was a wonderful thing he's he's
he's probably had some very good
circumstances in luck
and then we reverse it for ourselves
when i do something great
it's due to my character and when i do
something shitty it's due to my
circumstances
and we all do this it's one of the most
powerful things we do
so we have to constantly and when i'm
doing my
bias noting there's so many days when
the
the bias that comes up for me is the
fundamental attribution error the
fundamental attribution error again
and again and again and so when we're
asking this question about other people
what we need to do is ask it
dialogically
there have been large periods of my life
where i wasn't pursuing an examined life
what was going on in me
why was i doing that was it just because
i have a flawed character
no the fundamental attribution error is
actually going to help you it's going to
help you look around
for the circumstances and the factors
and the causes
but don't forget that transfer that back
to the other people
right well i remember i acted this way
and i was really hurt
and you know i i was dealing with
something that
initially overwhelmed me an aspect of
fate
and that's why i was bought like i had
body armor that's why i didn't examine
this
right well it's plausible that that's
what's going on for other people
and when we start to understand them by
reversing the fundamental attribution
error
we can ask this question in a fashion
that is much more conducive to the
generation of compassion it's not
easy the fundamental attribution is
really hard
and for somebody like me who's you know
got rejection sensitivity disorder
socially phobic i'm i i i'm so
prone to being defensive
it takes a lot it takes work
and practice to do this
but here's what's encouraging we are all
deeply susceptible anybody who's saying
i don't do that
read the literature please we all do it
and that means we should we're all
in concert together trying to help each
other to overcome the fundamental
attribution error
as much as possible so i hope that was
helpful
i want to thank you all for joining i
want to thank my
beloved friend techno mage ammar my
beloved friend
my beloved friend and son jason it's
funny when your children start to become
some of your best friends
it's an interesting change in your life
um
they're doing so much i hope the
technology we're getting better and
better pete please be patient
this is the last of the weekday classes
i'm not going to repeat everything i've
already said at length just
just to say once again i love this
i love the sangha i'm so proud of what
we have done together so thank you very
much but it's not over
on the 12th 10 a.m eastern time
we're picking it up and we're continuing
on through the transformative
aspirational journey through the wisdom
of hypatia
please subscribe to the channel to be
notified of the next video also if
you're not opposed to it in principle
follow me on twitter for any update on
the streams
invite others who might benefit by
sharing this series with them
it's very important that people join the
discord server that's where the daily
sits the lectio
divinas are taking place the moving
practices yoga
the philosophical contemplative
companionships are going to be home
there
please remember continuity of practice
is more important than sheer quantity of
practice
don't hold yourself to the standard of
harsh perfectionism
but a virtuous friendship because
there's no enemy
worse than your own mind and body
there's no friend
no encouraging ally no genuine
philosophical contemplative companion
on the path as good as your own mind and
body
be lamps unto yourselves and to each
other i'll see you on saturday the 12th
at 10 a.m eastern time take care
everyone
you